The following story will be about an easy-chair.
As Péter Váró said at the beginning (of the presentation series)
if we look at objects differently, they can change or they will change.
Is anyone here thinks about this easy-chair as something other than a chair?
Here, look. Like drop of water or something.
I won't give the answer away. This is an association game, what comes to your mind when you look at it?
(somebody shouts from the back rows)
Say what? Ok, I think we should hear the story
from the designer who had a simple problem and found a very simple solution to it
He just wanted to sit down, but there was nothing to sit down on. So he did something about it.
The next presenter is Géza Csire.
Three years ago, I finished my university studies and I had to move out of the dormitory.
And I moved into... this
As an upstart designer this itsy bitsy odd looking green room annoyed me greatly
and I felt really bad that this is all I can afford.
So, I decided that my first project as a designer
will be to revamp this room. I started with the walls, of course.
After that, because there were no lampshades I decided to install a chrome hemisphere lamp
that is going to cut it. It would look great in this environment.
I went to IKEA to buy one and thought it will be awesome.
Unfortunately, as I have reached the lamp section I realized I cannot afford to buy any of them.
As I was leaving I  have stumbled upon some salad bowls,
chrome hemisphere salad bowls.
They were way cheaper, so I bought one, I drilled a hole at the bottom and I had the lamp of my dreams.
Exalted by my success, I made a curtain valance from a broomstick.
Necessity inspires, doesn't it?
I was given a matters so I don't have to sleep on the floor.
I really didn't like it at all.
It was ugly. If I had a guest it needed to be put away or I had to make the bed, which I don't like either.
I thought I have my next challenge to turn it into an armchair.
So, I started thinking about it.
I put a big sheet of paper on the wall and I started to drew all kinds of tricky mechanisms onto it.
I thought long and hard and I was proud of myself for thinking of so many different things.
But none of it came through. After two months it seemed everything would need drilling and carving.
I would have to be precise and buy more stuff to make them.
This seemed too much and I wanted a simple solution.
I started giving up thinking it might not even have a slick solution.
The place where I lived was not only small, but it was also very far from the city center.
I have spent almost two hours commuting every day. That was a lot.
I thought it was to much to just let it got to waste,
therefore, I started different projects. For instance, drawing the strangers I was traveling with
and everything that they reminded me of.
Some people gave me business cards, and were happy about it, some people lashed out at me, saying I had not right to draw their portraits.
So, I moved on to a different project. I started folding different kinds of objects.
My first thought was whether I could fold a cylinder and break it in a 90 degree angle,
without having to cut the paper so I won't cockle it,
instead I would get a sort of cylinder along the fold.
I took a piece of paper, rectangle shaped, and folded it along the side to get a cylinder
and as an experiment I pressed in one of the sides.
I looked at it: this is a chair. If it was big enough, I could sit on it.
While opening it would give me a bed.
So, I got off the tram and I went into a draper's shop.
I bought some dot snaps because it takes only a hammer to attach them,
I affixed them onto the edge of my mattress cover
and there you have it, the first prototype of my easy-chair.
I made this grey version later.
I loved it very much because I didn't need to make my bed ever again.
More than that if anyone came to visit and my room wasn't tidy, I could take all my stuff and put them inside the bed.
I rolled it up and the room was tidy.
It wasn't the first object I made. During my university studies I entered into competitions with a shelf and a lamp
Both of them won the LG design award, so I wrote my thesis working with them.
For that the Hungarian TV sought me out. They wanted to come to my place and film in my room
because I could show them interesting things.
I thought it would be great. I could show them my chair
then it would immediately become a product.
For my thesis work was also a chair, and people often contact me because of that. This chair became famous on the internet
and these people say they could set up a production line, and things like that. But as long as I don't have a prototype I can't negotiate with companies.
For it is hard to sell if they can't sit on it.
So, these things get stuck, however, the easy-chair already has a prototype so I can turn into a product immediately.
This chair could be transformed into a table
and these tables could be put next to one another to make a different table or form blocks like this.
Moreover, they could be arranged in different styles.
So, it is an interesting concept that became famous for a good reason.
But I did not have the time or the energy to make one, so I started experimenting with the easy-chair.
However, nobody sought me out, no investors, no manufacturers who would be interested in selling this product.
In the meantime, Péter Molnár and I founded the Maform design studio.
As we didn't know what to do with this studio,
we took every opportunity we could get.
Among them was the competition of Misker Festival in Belgrad for real "balkanian" ideas. I sent them this.
They loved it and replied immediately, asking me to send them one because
they want to present it on an exhibition in two months time.
I had this dilemma, I was happy that they wanted to exhibit it,
but if I gave them my easy-chair, then...
I didn't want to sleep on the floor.
So, I started looking for a manufacturer, to make another one for me,
to sew a zipper on the side of a foam mattress.
I didn't want to carry it around in sheets. They couldn't understand what I wanted from my emails, it was difficult to communicate via telephone,
and they didn't believe that it makes any sense based on the photos either.
So, I had to take it with me to show them what it was about.
I wanted to leave the sheets at home hence I bought a flowerpot,
which would substitute for the sheets, besides I could roll the whole mattress into it.
I got it on my back and went off to find manufacturers
who would sew a zipper on it. I received different offers from 40-50 thousand HUF.
50 thousand HUF to sew this onto that.
I was scratching my head, what were they thinking?
So, I looked far and wide till I ended up at small dressmaker's in Vác.
Where they finally understood that I just wanted to have a zipper sewed on the side of this mattress.
However, I came face to face with another problem, a pedantic seamstress.
It came in handy that I had to deal with people like this before because of the competitions,
mechanics or people working in different fields.
When I have sent the rendering of the shelf I designed to the mechanic in pdf.
This was only the first page of the pdf - and the rest -
The rest contained the technical documentation, how to make it, how it will become a good shelf.
The mechanic sent it back and said he can't do it based on a render.
I told him to look at the rest of the pages, but he kept failing to realize that they were there.
After a week's arguing I had to print it and send it to him.
Somehow, he saw more than the first page now.
Otherwise he's a good mechanic, obviously it's not his fault that he can't deal with these things.
For my next design project I started with sending the printed documentation.
They sent it back saying they would have to build a gigantic device to be able to make it,
and they couldn't afford such an expense for this project.
I sent them a crude drawing explaining them
that each element could be pulled on a cone, and there they have it.
Then they sent it back to me saying if it is indeed so simple I should do it.
And I did. Luckily, I am persistent in these matters.
But I had these problems during my university years too.
I designed a clock that has a hole in the middle where circles rotate inside one another.
Nobody believed that it could work, or it could hold together and somehow work out
Everybody wanted me to change it and I got fed up.
One evening I cut up some beer cans after I drunk their contents.
I folded them into nice little cylinders and used them to demonstrate how the clock works.
When they finally understood that it is actually a good idea they used a 3D-printer to make a working prototype of this clock for me.
I hope this will become a product someday too.
So, I fought my way through fusspots like these, and the seamstress was not my first one.
She said this can not be done.
I asked: why? It won't fit into the sewing machine, there are no sewing patterns like this, it won't work, it can't work.
We argued a day or so, I insisted that it can be done.
At the end of the day, I said: let me use the sewing machine and I will do it.
Then she said that I can't touch her machines.
So, she did what I asked and the very first prototype was made.
Later, I realized that it would be more stable if the zipper ran further up.
I returned to the seamstress for the modifications and
when she looked at it she said she did not make it.
This is not possible, something like this can't be done. She swore it wasn't her work.
She is an interesting person.
Fortunately, we got past her. I changed the flowerpot to cardboard barrel in the middle.
This version was ready in time for the competition in Belgrade and won an innovation award there.
I thought this would immediately turn into a product.
It has been awarded, there will be someone who wants to market it.
However, it took another year before it became known.
I needed a name for it,
"paq" because it is compact, fun-packed, and so on.
Besides, p-a-q upside down is b-e-d.
Even the logo can be turned into a bed.
After one year's work the BBDM Design Management took the product under their wings.
They organized proper manufacturing and distribution channels.
We tested it with many people
to see what they use it for. It turned out that the target audience is not really university students,
and it will be popular rather as a spare bed.
We put on the finishing touches at lunched the product at the end of April.
Since April distributors approached us from 11 countries.
This product is on sale in America, Canada, Singapore and Japan.
I was slack-jawed with awe that this product became so popular overnight.
For example in one of the TEDx-s in Los Angeles, all the participants listen to the presentations from chairs like this.
It became successful and I started thinking about the reason why.
How could it become so successful so fast? What is the secret?
Then it occurred to me that we all like stories, and every object has one.
These objects tell a story in one way or anther, which can be long or short.
The story of my easy-chair, with the empty room, the necessity, the struggles I had,
are so deeply entwined with this object as these few slides illustrate it.
We like those stories that are new, interesting, surprising, or just make us think.
And the really successful objects tell stories like this in a way we never heard before.
Thank you.
If I want to sit down, I rather sit on the floor than start thinking about stories.
How do these stories come to your mind?
How do they come to my mind?
They don't. What happens is that
I explore, experiment, I allow my brain to wander about what interest me.
I don't let my pre-existing knowledge to be my reference point.
From things you know, you can make things you know.
Instead I try to explore what is interesting, what might be new.
It's not new all the time, therefore, not all my ideas are inventions obviously.
There are boundaries, because I too started fiddling with mechanisms at first,
a bunch of constructive, geometric doo-hickeys that resulted chairs
following the topology of the already existing ones.
In contrast to this, the inspiration came from a different field, origami.
So, I rather just saw the solution than found out something great.
I hope we will see many of your solutions in the future,
let it be here or in other parts of the town.
Thank you for being here.
Subtitles: László Fekete
fekete.laszlo.08@gmail.com